{"tossups": [{"question": "The chief religious role of these people was dispelling chaos, or <em>isfet</em>, and maintaining harmony, or <em>ma'at</em>. These people wore the <em>pschent</em> crown, representing the northern and southern portions of their kingdom. One of these people established a monotheistic religion centered on the sun disk, Aten. These rulers were believed to be human incarnations of the gods Osiris and Ra. For ten points, name these kings who ruled Ancient Egypt.", "answer": "<b><u>Pharaoh</u></b> (prompt on \"King of Egypt\" or similar answers)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "An ultranationalist group named for blue examples of these objects supported Chiang Kai-Shek\u2019s New Life Movement. The Expedition of the Thousand was conducted by the Red [these objects], who followed Giuseppe Garibaldi. A 1922 March on Rome was led by Benito Mussolini and his followers, nicknamed for black [objects of this type]. For ten points, name this article of clothing whose \u201cBrown\u201d types were worn by the SA [[ESS-AY]].", "answer": "<b><u>Shirt</u></b>s [accept Blue <b><u>Shirt</u></b>s; accept Red <b><u>Shirt</u></b>s; accept Black <b><u>Shirt</u></b>s; accept Brown <b><u>Shirt</u></b>s; prompt on synonyms like \"tunics\" or \"blouses\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man's father formed a short-lived alliance with Murad II until he was imprisoned. This man and his brother Radu were jailed as children, though the Ottomans released him after an invasion of his homeland by John Hunyadi. The envoys of this man's childhood friend, Sultan Mehmed II, were impaled on stakes by this <em>voivode</em> [[VOY-vohd]]. The ruler of independent Wallachia [[woh-LEH-kyuh]] and a Romanian national hero was, for ten points, what infamous warlord who inspired a vampire created by Bram Stoker?", "answer": "<b><u>Vlad the Impaler</u></b> (or <b><u>Vlad Tepes</u></b> [[TEH-pesh]]; accept <b><u>Vlad III</u></b>; accept <b><u>Vlad</u></b> <b><u>Dracula</u></b>; or <b><u>Vlad Dr\u0103culea</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on \"Vlad Dracul\" NOTE: \"Vlad Dracul\" or \"Vlad the Dragon\" was Vlad the Impaler's father)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This artist depicted a chain of the Order of the Golden Fleece adorning the neck of the title royal in <em>Philip IV in Brown and Silver</em>. One of this man's earlier artistic focuses was on scenes from the kitchen, as shown in his painting <em>An Old Woman Cooking Eggs</em>. One of this man's works shows the ladies-in-waiting of La Infanta Margherita in the court of her father. For ten points, name this Spanish Golden Age artist who created the painting <em>Las</em> <em>Meninas</em>.", "answer": "Diego <b><u>Vel\u00e1zquez</u></b> (or Diego Rodr\u00edguez de Silva y <b><u>Vel\u00e1zquez</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Edward R. Murrow ran an episode of <em>See It Now</em> that criticized this politician for his interrogation of Annie Lee Moss. This man, who ran for Senate on the slogan \"Congress needs a tail-gunner,\" was chastised by Joseph Welch with the question, \u201chave you no sense of decency?\u201d For ten points, name this Wisconsin senator who claimed to have a list of 205 known communists in the state department, driving the Second Red Scare.", "answer": "Joseph <b><u>McCarthy</u></b> (or Joseph Raymond <b><u>McCarthy</u></b>; accept \"Tail-Gunner Joe\" <b><u>McCarthy</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A holder of this position became the highest-ranking U.S. official to visit Antarctica in 2016, staying overnight at McMurdo Station. One of these people claimed the U.S. went to Afghanistan to \"deal with the folks who attacked us on 9/11 and we have succeeded in that mission\" in response to comparisons of the fall of Kabul with the capture of Saigon. Antony Blinken and John Kerry are recent Democrats to hold this office. For ten points, name this position, the primary foreign minister of the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>Secretary</u></b> of <b><u>State</u></b> (accept <b><u>State Secretary</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Sixth century Byzantine monks established a pilgrimage site for this figure's purported burial site on Mount Nebo. While this figure was tending the sheep of his father-in-law, a bush caught fire without burning and told this man \"I am who I am.\" This Biblical figure caused a series of plagues in one country, and he parted the Red Sea in Exodus 14. For ten points, name this Biblical prophet who delivered the Israelites from Egyptian slavery.", "answer": "<b><u>Moses</u></b> (accept <b><u>Moshe</u></b> Rabbenu; accept <b><u>Musa</u></b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This ruler's armies forced the Truce of Ratisbon, which ceded Luxembourg to his country and concluded the War of the Reunions. This monarch survived the Fronde [[\"FROND\"]] Rebellion in his youth and employed the engineer Vauban [[VOH-BAHN]] to create star forts along his country's frontier. This king ordered his nobles to inhabit the massive Palace at Versailles. For ten points, name this \"Sun King\" of France, a long-lived absolutist monarch.", "answer": "<b><u>Louis XIV</u></b> [[the fourteenth[/a] (accept (accept <b><u>Louis the Great</u></b>; or <b><u>Louis le</u></b> <b><u>Grand</u></b>; accept <b><u>Louis, the Sun King</u></b> or <b><u>Louis, le Roi Soleil</u></b> before \"Sun King\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man's skillful turning maneuvers resulted in a decisive victory at Kennesaw Mountain, which Liddell Hart cited in calling this man the first \"modern general.\" While leading the Division of the Mississippi, this man's Special Field Orders No. 15 resulted in the phrase \"forty acres and a mule.\" In the wake of the Battle of Atlanta, this man's forces undertook the \"March to the Sea\" to the Confederate port of Savannah. The \"scorched earth tactic\" was utilized by, for ten points, which Union general during the Civil War?", "answer": "William Tecumseh <b><u>Sherman</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city was governed by a constitution known as the Great Rhetra, written by Lycurgus. Children in this city ate \"black soup\" and were forced into the Agoge [[ah-GOG-geh]] training system from the age of seven. Elected officials known as <em>Ephors</em> governed this city, which was ruled by two kings. Ritual killings of the Helot underclass occurred in, for ten points, what militaristic ancient city state which rivaled Athens?", "answer": "<b><u>Sparta</u></b> (accept <b><u>Lacedaemon</u></b>; or <b><u>Laconike</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Earl Grey tea is named for one holder of this position, while another names the capital of the Australian state of Victoria. A Canadian, Andrew Bonar Law, held this position for 211 days between 1922 and 1923. As a result of the Brexit controversy, Theresa May resigned from this position in July 2019. For ten points, name this position, held since 2019 by Boris Johnson from 10 Downing Street, the head of the British government.", "answer": "<b><u>Prime Minister</u></b> of the <b><u>United Kingdom</u></b> (accept <b><u>British Prime Minister</u></b>; accept <b><u>Great Britain</u></b> in place of \"United Kingdom\"; accept <b><u>PM</u></b> in place of \"Prime Minister\"; accept <b><u>UK</u></b> in place of \"United Kingdom\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "Just after this event, a similar event occurred on the urging of Benjamin Rush in Philadelphia. This event's participants attacked the <em>Eleanor</em>, <em>Beaver</em>, and <em>Dartmouth</em>, and it was planned at the Old South Meeting House. Conducted by Sons of Liberty dressed as Native Americans, for ten points, what was this destructive act of protest in which a shipment of the namesake product was destroyed in a Massachusetts harbor?", "answer": "<b><u>Boston Tea Party</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Explorer Henri Mouhot [[moo-HOH]] was the first westerner to discover this site while serving as a missionary in Battambang, and he claimed it was a temple which \"rivalled Solomon's.\" This site, a representation of Mount Meru, was built by Suryavarman II [[soor-yah-VAHR-mahn the second]] under the influence of Chola advisors from the Indian subcontinent. The Khmer [[KMARE]] Empire built, for ten points, what palatial complex seen on the modern flag of Cambodia?", "answer": "<b><u>Angkor Wat</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This country fought a month-long conflict with Ecuador in 1995 known as the Cenepa War. Beginning in 1996, the Japanese embassy in this country was the scene of a hostage crisis that lasted for four months. In this nation, Chilean Bernardo O'Higgins and Argentine general Jos\u00e9 de San Mart\u00edn [[mar-TEEN]] crossed the Andes to help liberate this country from Spanish control. For ten points, name this South American country that was once the heartland of the Inca.", "answer": "<b><u>Peru</u></b> (accept Republic of <b><u>Peru</u></b>; or Rep\u00fablica del <b><u>Per\u00fa</u></b>; accept <b><u>Piruw</u></b> Ripuwlika; accept <b><u>Piruw</u></b> Suyu)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This city was the center of the Affair of the Placards, which resulted from rising tensions between Catholics and Protestants. In 1871, over ten thousand people were massacred when a \"Commune\" in this city was brutally crushed. The wildcat strikes of May, 1968 were centered on this city's student population. In November 2015, an ISIS attack at a soccer stadium and the Bataclan Theatre led to over a hundred deaths in this city. For ten points, name this French city where Notre Dame caught fire in 2019.", "answer": "<b><u>Paris</u></b> (accept <b><u>Paris</u></b> Commune)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The southern portion of this historical kingdom was ceded to the British in the Simla Accords. The warlord Ma Bufang held a future leader of this kingdom hostage until a ransom of Silver Dragon coins was paid. The Seventeen Points Agreement was negotiated between this kingdom's leader, Tenzin Gyatso, and the government of Mao Zedong. The Dalai Lama [[DAH-lee LAH-muh]] leads the government-in-exile of, for ten points, what historical kingdom currently controlled by China?", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Tibet</u></b> (accept <b><u>Bod</u></b> [[BOH]]; accept <b><u>X\u012bz\u00e0ng</u></b>; prompt on \"\u00dc\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "One of the few survivors of this battle were Susanna Dickinson and a slave named  Joe, both of whom were spared by an enemy commander.  That commander at this battle would later be defeated at the Battle of San Jacinto [[hah- SEEN-toe]]. The location of this battle was depicted on a stamp in 1856 to celebrate the  anniversary of Texan statehood. A fortified mission was attacked in, for ten points, what  battle of the Texan War of Independence that would go on to become a famous battle cry?", "answer": "Battle of the <b><u>Alamo</u></b> (accept \"Remember the <b><u>Alamo</u></b>\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The dead of these people were buried with maize in their mouth, while this people's  Caracol site shows signs of post-mortem bloodletting. Women in this culture travelled to the  pilgrimage site of the fertility goddess Ixchel [[EEKS-chehl]] on the isle of Cozumel. The  underworld of Xibalba [[shee-BAHL-bah]] is traversed by this people's mythic \"Hero Twins\"  in the compendium, <em>Popul Vuh</em>. For ten points, these myths were carved in the monumental  architecture of what Mesoamerican civilization?", "answer": "<b><u>Maya</u></b>n (accept K'iche <b><u>Maya</u></b>; accept Classical <b><u>Maya</u></b>ns)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Chaturanga was an early version of this game, whose early twentieth century</u></b> <b><u>champions included Cuban prodigy Jos\u00e9 Ra\u00fal Capablanca. In 2013, World Champion</u></b> <b><u>Vishi Anand was defeated by Norwegian (+)</u> Magnus Carlsen, who claims the highest rating ever in this game. The 1972 World Championship in this game between Boris Spassky and Bobby Fischer (*) </b>was considered a \"battle\" of the Cold War. For ten points, name this \"Game of Kings\" which boomed in popularity thanks to the Netflix hit <em>The Queen's</em> <em>Gambit</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Chess</u></b> (accept Indian <b><u>Chess</u></b>; accept <b><u>Shogi</u></b> or <b><u>Xiangqi</u></b> before \"Cuban\")", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>While this man was enrolled at West Point, he designed the M1913 Cavalry</u></b> <b><u>Saber and competed in the 1912 Summer Olympics. This man controversially</u></b> <b><u>organized Task Force (+)</u> Baum to rescue his son-in-law, John K. Waters. This general died shortly after being paralyzed in a low-speed car wreck. Infamously chastised for slapping two shell-shocked (*) </b>soldiers, for ten points, name this successful American general known as \"Old Blood and Guts.\"", "answer": "George S(mith) <b><u>Patton</u></b> Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The polymath Pindar labelled this body the \"Inhospitable Sea\" and considered</u></b> <b><u>travelling in it to be an ill-omen. A \"deluge\" hypothesis involving this body of water</u></b> <b><u>might have inspired the story of (+)</u> Noah's Ark. A Russian victory on this body of water during the Battle of Sinope [[see-NOH-pee]] led to the British and French entering the Crimean War. The Montreux [[mon-TROO]] Convention allowed foreign vessels to pass to and from, (*) </b>for ten points, what sea which borders countries like Ukraine and Turkey?", "answer": "<b><u>Black</u></b> Sea (accept <b><u>Chyornoye</u></b> more; accept <b><u>Karadeniz</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>The statue</u> </b><em><b><u>Lifting of the Veil of Ignorance</u></b></em><b><u> at this location depicts a formerly</u></b> <b><u>enslaved man being shown the proper path by its founder. This site's Moton Field</u></b> <b><u>served as training grounds for its namesake \"Airmen\" who (+)</u> fought in the Second World War. An unethical study named for this institution left syphilis untreated in four hundred Black male sharecroppers for forty years to study its effects. George Washington (*) </b>Carver studied at, for ten points, which Alabama university once led by Booker T. Washington?", "answer": "<b><u>Tuskegee</u></b> Institute (accept <b><u>Tuskegee</u></b> University)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>After the 1979 overthrow of Jean-B\u00e9del Bokassa [[zhen-BEH-dehl boh-KAH-</u><u>suh]], this man became the world's only reigning \"Emperor.\" This man was almost</u></b> <b><u>deposed in the Ky\u016bj\u014d [[KYOO-joh]] incident, (+)</u> which occurred prior to the \"Jewel Voice\" broadcast. This son of Taisho, [[\"TIE\"-shoh]] and grandson of Meiji [[MEH-jee]], became the only ruler on the Chrysanthemum (*) </b>Throne to experience a foreign occupation after his country was bombed with nuclear weapons. For ten points, name this Japanese emperor during World War Two.", "answer": "<b><u>Hirohito</u></b> (accept <b><u>Sh\u014dwa</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The so-called \"English Achilles,\" John Talbot, led a campaign in this century</u></b> <b><u>which ended with the disastrous Battle of Castillon [[cah-steh-YOHN]], leading to the</u></b> <b><u>loss of (+)</u> Aquitaine. English longbowmen and the deployment of wooden stakes by the British proved vital at the Battle of Agincourt [[ah-jinn-KOHR]], a clash during this century. The Hundred Years' War (*) </b>ended in, for ten points, what century of the late Middle Ages?", "answer": "<b><u>Fifteen</u></b>th Century (accept <b><u>1400</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The</u> </b><em><b><u>Periplus of the Erythraean</u></b></em><b><u> [[eh-rith-REH-an]]</u> </b><em><b><u>Sea</u></b></em><b><u> recounts how Rome</u></b> <b><u>traded for this commodity with the Chera Dynasty's merchants on the Malabar Coast.</u></b> <b><u>Zheng He's [[ZHEHNG HUHS]] voyage through the Indian (+)</u> Ocean led to this spice transforming from a luxury item to a common household product in Ming China. This spice was colloquially known as \"black gold\" in the early modern period by Europeans. Salt is (*) </b>historically paired with, for ten points, what spice?", "answer": "Black <b><u>Pepper</u></b> (accept <b><u>Pepper</u></b>corn)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Flights from this nation to Belarus were halted in November 2021 to stop</u></b> <b><u>Middle Eastern migrants from entering the EU. A 2016 coup attempt in this nation</u></b> <b><u>may have been manufactured by its president to purge the military of enemies. The</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Kurdish PKK party fought an asymmetrical war with this nation's government, which is led by Recep Tayyip Erdo\u011fan [[EHR-doh-wahn]]. ISIS (*) </b>may have perpetrated the 2015 Ankara Bombings in, for ten points, what Anatolian nation?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Turkey</u></b> (or <b><u>T\u00fcrkiye</u></b> Cumhuriyeti)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man signed the Act Prohibiting Importation of Slaves, which</u></b> <b><u>unintentionally increased the domestic slave trade. In response to British threats to</u></b> <b><u>U.S. shipping, this man signed the (+)</u> Embargo Act. In his most famous document, this man wrote that all men have the right to \"Life, Liberty, and the Pursuit of (*) </b>Happiness.\" For ten points, name this primary author of the Declaration of Independence, the third president of the United States.", "answer": "Thomas <b><u>Jefferson</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}